All human life,
كل حياة البشر،
all life, depends on plants.
كل الحياة، تعتمد على النباتات .
Let me try to convince you of that in a few seconds.
دعوني أحاول إقناعكم بذلك خلال ثواني معدودة.
Just think for a moment.
فكّروا لوهلة.
It doesn't matter whether you live in a small African village,
لا يهم اذا ما كنتم تعيشون في قرية أفريقية صغيرة،
or you live in a big city,
أو تعيشون في مدينة كبيرة،
everything comes back to plants in the end:
كل شئ يعود الى النباتات في النهاية.
whether it's for the food, the medicine,
سواء كان ذلك من أجل الغذاء، الدواء ،
the fuel, the construction, the clothing, all the obvious things;
الوقود، الإنشاءات، الملابس، كل الأشياء المعتادة،
or whether it's for the spiritual and recreational things
أو سواء كان من أجل الأشياء الروحية أو الترويحية
that matter to us so much;
التي تعني الكثير بالنسبة لنا،
or whether it's soil formation,
أو اذا ما كانت تكوين التربة،
or the effect on the atmosphere,
أو تأثير ذلك على الطقس،
or primary production.
أو الإنتاج الأولي .
Damn it, even the books here are made out of plants.
اللعنة، حتى الكتب هنا مصنوعة من النباتات.
All these things, they come back to plants.
كل هذه الاشياء، تعود الى النباتات.
And without them we wouldn't be here.
وبدونها لا يمكن أن نكون هنا.
Now plants are under threat.
الآن النباتات مهددة.
They're under threat because of changing climate.
أنها مهددة بسبب تغيّر المناخ.
And they are also under threat because they are sharing a planet
وهي أيضاً مهددة لأنها تتشارك الأرض
with people like us.
مع أناس مثلنا.
And people like us want to do things that destroy plants,
والناس أمثالنا يريدون فعل أشياء تقوم بتدمير الأرض،
and their habitats.
ومواطنها.
And whether that's because of food production,
وسواء كان ذلك بسبب إنتاج الغذاء
or because of the introduction of alien plants
أو بسبب إدخال النباتات الغريبة
into places that they really oughtn't be,
الى أماكن لا يجب حقاً أن تكون فيها،
or because of habitats being used for other purposes --
أو بسبب أن مواطنها تُستخدم لأغراض أخرى،
all these things are meaning that plants have to adapt,
وكل هذه الأشياء تعني أن على النباتات المقاومة،
or die, or move.
أو الموت، أو الإنتقال.
And plants sometimes find it rather difficult to move
وتجد النباتات بعض الأحيان من الصعب الإنتقال
because there might be cities and other things in the way.
لأنه ربما توجد مدن وأشياء أخرى في طريقها.
So if all human life depends on plants,
لذا اذا كانت كل الحياة البشرية تعتمد على النباتات،
doesn't it make sense that perhaps we should try to save them?
أليس من المعقول أننا ربما نحاول حمايتها؟
I think it does.
أعتقد أننا يجب أن نفعل.
And I want to tell you about a project to save plants.
وما أريد إخباركم به هو مشروع حفظ النباتات.
And the way that you save plants
والطريقة التي تحمي بها النباتات
is by storing seeds.
هو عبر تخزين البذور.
Because seeds, in all their diverse glory,
لأن البذور، في كل مجد تنوعها،
are plants' futures.
هي نباتات آجلة.
All the genetic information for future generations of plants
كل المعلومات الجينية للأجيال المستقبلية من النباتات
are held in seeds.
محفوظة في البذور.
So here is the building;
لذا فهذا هو البناء.
it looks rather unassuming, really.
ويبدو متواضعاً حقاً.
But it goes down below ground many stories.
لكنه يمتد لما تحت الأرض لطوابق.
And it's the largest seed bank in the world.
وهذا هو أكبر بنك لتخزين البذور في العالم.
It exists not only in southern England,
موجود ليس فقط في جنوب إنجلترا،
but distributed around the world. I'll come to that.
لكنه متوزع في كل أرجاء العالم. سأعود لهذا.
This is a nuclear-proof facility.
أنها منشأة إختبارات نووية.
God forbid that it should have to withstand that.
لا سمح الله يجب عليها أن تتحمل ذلك.
So if you're going to build a seed bank, you have to decide
لذا فاذا كنتم محتاجون لبناء بنك للبذور، يجب عليك تقرير
what you're going to store in it. Right?
ما يجب عليك تخزينه. صحيح؟
And we decided that what we want to store first of all,
وقد قررنا أن ما يجب علينا تخزينه بداية،
are the species that are most under threat.
هو الكائنات المهددة بالإنقراض بشدة.
And those are the dry land species.
وتلك هي كائنات الأراضي الجافة.
So first of all we did deals
لذا فبداية قمنا بعقد إتفاقيات
with 50 different countries.
مع 50 دولة مختلفة.
It means negotiating with heads of state,
هذا يعني التفاوض مع رؤساء الدول،
and with secretaries of state in 50 countries
ووزراء الخارجية ل 50 دولة
to sign treaties.
لتوقيع معاهدات.
We have 120 partner institutions all over the world,
لدينا 120 مؤسسة شريكة في كل أنحاء العالم،
in all those countries colored orange.
وكل تلك الدول معلمة باللون البرتقالي.
People come from all over the world to learn,
يأتي الناس من كل أنحاء العالم ليتعلموا.
and then they go away and plan exactly how
وبعدها يرجعون ويخططون كيف بالضبط
they're going to collect these seeds.
سيقوموا بأخذ هذه البذور.
They have thousands of people all over the world
لديهم آلالاف البشر في كل أنحاء العالم
tagging places where those plants are said to exist.
يذهبون لأماكن حيث توجد هذه النباتات.
They search for them. They find them in flower.
يبحثون عنها. يجدونها في زهرة.
And they go back when their seeds have arrived.
ويرجعون عندما تصل بذورهم.
And they collect the seeds. All over the world.
ويجمعون البذور. في كل العالم.
The seeds -- some of if is very untechnical.
البذور-- بعضها حساس جداً.
You kind of shovel them all in to bags and dry them off.
تقوم بتجميعها في حقائب وتجففها.
You label them. You do some high-tech things here and there,
تضع عليها أسم. تقوم بتطبيق بعض التقنيات عليها هنا وهناك.
some low-tech things here and there.
بعض الأشياء اليدوية عليها هنا وهناك.
And the main thing is that you have to dry them
والشئ الرئيسي هو أنك يجب أن تجففها
very carefully, at low temperature.
بكل حرص، في درجات حرارة منخفضة.
And then you have to store them
وبعدها يتوجب عليك تخزينها
at about minus 20 degrees C --
في درجة حرارة حوالي ناقص 20 درجة تحت الصفر--
that's about minus four Fahrenheit, I think --
ذلك ناقص أربعة درجات بمقياس فهرنهايت، أعتقد--
with a very critically low moisture content.
مع إنخفاض نسبة الرطوبة بشدة.
And these seeds will be able to germinate,
وسيكون بمقدور هذه البذور الإنبات،
we believe, with many of the species,
كما نعتقد، مع العديد من الكائنات،
in thousands of years,
عبر آلالاف السنين،
and certainly in hundreds of years.
وتحديداً عبر مئات السنين.
It's no good storing the seeds if you don't know they're still viable.
ليس جيدا تخزين البذور إذا كنت لا تعرف انها قابلة للحياة.
So every 10 years we do germination tests
لذا فكل 10 سنوات نقوم بإختبارات التنبيت
on every sample of seeds that we have.
في كل عينة لدينا من البذور.
And this is a distributed network.
وهذه شبكة متوزعة.
So all around the world people are doing the same thing.
ولذا فالناس من كل أرجاء العالم يفعلون نفس الشئ.
And that enables us to develop germination protocols.
وهذا يساعدنا في تطوير برتوكولات للتنبيت.
That means that we know the right combination of heat
ذلك يعني أننا نعرف التشكيلة الصحيحة للحراراة
and cold and the cycles that you have to get
والبرودة والدورة التي يجب أن تمر بها
to make the seed germinate.
لجعل البذرة تنبت.
And that is very useful information.
وتلك معلومات مهمة للغاية.
And then we grow these things,
وبعد ذلك نقوم بزرع هذه الأشياء،
and we tell people, back in the countries where these seeds have come from,
ونخبر الناس، في بلدانهم التي جاءت منها البذور،
"Look, actually we're not just storing this
" أنظروا، في الواقع نحن لا نخزن هذا
to get the seeds later,
لنأخذ البذور لاحقاً،
but we can give you this information about
لكن بإستطاعتنا تقديم المعلومات لكم حول
how to germinate these difficult plants."
كيفية تنبيت هذه النباتات الصعبة."
And that's already happening.
وهذا يحدث بالفعل.
So where have we got to?
اذا الى أين يجب أن نتوجه؟
I am pleased to unveil that our three billionth seed --
أنا سعيد بالكشف عن أن بذورنا التي تبلغ ثلاثة بلايين،
that's three thousand millionth seed --
هذا يعني ثلاثة آلالاف مليون بذرة،
is now stored.
الآن مُخزّنة.
Ten percent of all plant species on the planet,
10 في المائة من كائنات الأرض من النباتات.
24,000 species are safe;
24 ألف كائن محمي.
30,000 species, if we get the funding, by next year.
30 ألف كائن، اذا حصلنا على الدعم، بحلول العام القادم.
Twenty-five percent of all the world's plants, by 2020.
25 في المائة من كل نباتات العالم، بحلول 2020.
These are not just crop plants,
هذه ليست نباتات محاصيل فقط،
as you might have seen stored in Svalbard in Norway --
مثل ما رأيتم ربما في سفالبارد في النرويج.
fantastic work there.
عمل ممتاز هناك.
This is at least 100 times bigger.
هذا على الأقل 100 مرة أكبر.
We have thousands of collections that have been sent out
لدينا آلالاف المجموعات التي أُرسلت
all over the world:
الى كل أرجاء العالم.
drought-tolerant forest species sent to Pakistan and Egypt;
كائنات الغابات الجافة المتعايشة أُرسلت الى باكستان ومصر.
especially photosynthetic-efficient plants
خصوصاً نباتات التمثيل الضوئي الكفوء
come here to the United States;
تأتي هنا الى الولايات المتحدة.
salt-tolerant pasture species sent to Australia;
أنواع الكائنات المتعايشة مع الملوحة أُرسلت الى استراليا.
the list goes on and on.
وتستمر القائمة الى أكثر وأكثر.
These seeds are used for restoration.
هذه البذور أُستخدمت للإحياء.
So in habitats that have already been damaged,
لذا ففي الأراضي التي دُمّرت فيها بالفعل،
like the tall grass prairie here in the USA,
مثل مرج العشب طويل القامة، هنا في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
or in mined land in various countries,
أو في الأراضي المنقّبة في عدة دول،
restoration is already happening because of these species --
الإحياء حاصل بالفعل بسبب هذه الكائنات.
and because of this collection.
وبسبب هذا التجميع.
Some of these plants, like the ones on the bottom
بعض هذه النباتات، مثل تلك في الأسفل
to the left of your screen,
الى شمال الشاشة،
they are down to the last few remaining members.
أنها بعض الأنواع القليلة المتبقية.
The one where the guy is collecting seeds there on the truck,
تلك التي يجمع ذلك الشخص بذورها على الشاحنة،
that is down to about 30 last remaining trees.
أنقرضت لحوالي فقط 30 شجرة متبقية فقط.
Fantastically useful plant,
نبات مفيد بصورة خيالية،
both for protein and for medicine.
من أجل البروتين والطب.
We have training going on in China, in the USA,
لدينا تدريب جاري في الصين، في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
and many other countries.
والعديد من البلدان الأخرى.
How much does it cost?
كم يكلف ذلك؟
2,800 dollars per species is the average.
2800 دولار للكائن في المتوسط.
I think that's cheap, at the price.
أعتقد أن هذا رخيص، حول السعر.
And that gets you all the scientific data
وذلك يقدم لك كل البيانات العلمية
that goes with it.
المصاحبة لها.
The future research is "How can we find
مستقبل البحث هو " كيف يمكننا إيجاد
the genetic and molecular markers
المعلمات الجينية والجزيئية،
for the viability of seeds,
من أجل بقاء البذور،
without having to plant them every 10 years?"
من دون الحوجة لزرعه كل 10 سنوات؟"
And we're almost there.
ونحن بصدد الوصول الى هناك.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)